all G of it is that our brains form
these neural networks these patterns of
firings and those dynamic patterns as
they unfold are the thoughts that we
have and when one of those patterns
arises it creates a global pattern that
global pattern is your emergent
understanding in the moment for that
global pattern to be coherent it must
suppress other global patterns it would
make it end coherent so now think about
political world view one person has a
conservative worldview they see things
with certain concepts then there are
these progressive concepts they're
incompatible with each other one must be
suppressed for the other to be active so
even at that conceptual level of how we
think about politics and morality all
these things this is happening in our
brains and that's why it's helpful for
us to know that this is happening so
it's a we say there were open-minded
we're really well I don't say when we're
open-minded what we're doing it's
sometimes called channel switching to
differentiate from multitasking cuz you
can't really multitask if you think
about it multitasking would mean that
you're splitting your attention to two
things at exactly the same tenth time
the only way that can work is through
different sense modalities your hand can
be doing one thing wars during another
and you can keep those somewhat separate
but I'm pretty limited and you run out
of attention pretty quickly but mode
shifting or channel shifting is when you
go from thinking in one way to thinking
in another so you're doing channel
shifting when you jump back and forth
between these images and so you can take
on different perspectives it's actually
one of the reasons why learning a second
language helps people have more empathy
is that they're doing / sweat
perspective shifting and their brain
develops a greater agility for it but
they're still only having one
perspective at a time
so it's important to just understand
that you know this is basic stuff about
the brain but look how powerful it is
right it's huge so so those are just a
couple examples of of how our brains
work they tell us something about how
human beings work and they're probably
useful for a social change now I'd like
to to talk for a moment about and one of
the ideas it's out there as about how
the mind works that I think you'll
recognize in anthropology they call this
a folk theory just kind of a common
sense understanding of the mind so I'm
gonna walk through it real quick and see
if you recognize it so first of all we
have this idea that thought is conscious
like we can know our own thoughts we can
contemplate and introspect about our
thoughts yeah it's a pretty common idea
that's another one is it thought is
literal just like the idea i'm having
maps and a one-to-one way onto the world
i'm thinking about a red cards because
i've actually seen in a red car and it
might even be a red mazda or red
Corvette but it's a specific one it's
idea that our thoughts map literally
onto the world it's a kind of common
idea makes sense right another one we
hear a lot as it thought is
dispassionate to reason effectively we
have to suppress our emotions that's
that's one that's out there you know we
probably her down before I like this one
it's a DA thought is universal so we all
reason in the same ways so if I present
the facts to you you'll reason to the
same conclusion I do and and finally
this one's a little more subtle thought
is logical and more specifically that
thought works through the way that
symbolic logic works that we have this
kind of truth propositional structure
and you know the interesting thing about
all of these and I come from Missouri so
i'll quote one of my fellow brethren of
missouri is it's not so much the things
we don't know but the things we know
that just ain't so right Mark Twain and
see the funny thing is we have this
common sense understanding of the mind
its pervasive in our culture every bit
of those every one of those things is
wrong it turns out that most of what we
call thought happens outside of
conscious awareness some estimates as
high as ninety-eight percent of the
cognitive processing in our brains
happens outside our own awareness
idea of the thought as literal is not
not true at all back in the late 70s
they discovered that thought is
profoundly metaphorical that we reason
by analogy from one part of our life
experience to another and that means
that thought is not dispassionate but
actually to reason effectively we have
to use emotions the way I like to
illustrate that is imagine you're at a
bar trying to get someone's phone number
and you're getting through that awkward
moment how can you do that without
emotions to guide how the situation is
unfolding you can't reason effectively
in social context without those emotions
about guilt shame pride happiness how
receptive as the other person those are
all emotional cues so we actually use a
motion to reason and so it turns out
that reasoning requires emotion and
theta thought is universal well if it's
metaphorical that means whichever
context were reasoning and will have its
own self-contained logic and so people
can reason differently in different
contexts and we find that happening all
the time and the idea that thought is
logical well thought was logical
politics would be rather different I
don't think I need a really elaborate
that one any further but you can see
that all these ideas are there in our
culture and they're wrong and and so so
we gotta this is kind of that's the
blind spot right as the things we know
that just ain't so so to get back the
big question how do we design for
large-scale change and I think they're
really two pieces one is we have to get
outside the boxes of our thinking
especially one of those boxes are wrong
like we have a container for thinking
that's not correct and then we have to
develop tools to use to apply these new
ways of thinking to the world and you
know so so to think about some of these
tools there's this framework that I got
to help develop with a guy named George
Lake off we call a cognitive policy and
you know in a really kind of big way
there's a lot of stuff happening here
but let's imagine no you can think about
how worldview works and the psychology
of identity and the norms and values
these different models we have for the
world all these different kinds of
knowledge we funnel them into a design
process that puts the user at the center
so the years in this case is the person
in their community and then we can
design for social change say do you have
cognitive policy is to take all this
understanding about how the mind works
and bring it into the design process so
how are people interacting with this
what are they thinking about how do they
feel about it how could we change the
structure of their environment the way
that Amazon did when they put that was
this review helpful and it's changed the
way that online review is work so you
know use this user centered design you
corporate all this knowledge into the
design process and you'll have a lot
better design at the end of the day so
this idea of cognitive policy is the
toolkit of all that knowledge though we
could bring together to do that design
work and we'll go through some more of
what those particular pieces might be as
we go through the day so another one
well really to give you a sense of how
this cognitive policy idea works let's
look an example I'll use social security
so we know social security is a policy
it's piece of legislation and it's got
an institution around it there's a way
it works but cognitively how does it
work what does it mean to people well
what it means to people is that you know
they work and they make money and they
pay into this big national community
piggy bank and then they know that when
they get old and retired that community
will take care of them and so this is
the way that people understand it and
this is part of their experience of
Social Security and so they learn things
like they learned that people who work
hard to be taken care of that we all do
better when we all do better and that
someone in a civil society should be
taken care of in their old age we have
these sets of values and moral
principles that are just intuitive and
the experience that people have with
Social Security you don't actually have
to teach them now the full logic of
Social Security they just get it when
money is garnished from their check and
they know it's going to take care of
them when they're old as long as it
still works and this is actually the
reason why social security has been so
hard to get rid of there has been a
concerted effort for about 20 years to
privatizing at rid of Social Security
and I can't do it because it's popular
people want it and why do they want it
because they understand it and they know
it's valuable so the cognitive policy
piece is the understandings and the
values and the priorities built into
their experience of it
then make it something that lasts for
them so a quick counter example would be
a don't no child left behind which was
designed to defund schools make it a bad
experience and move us to private high
school so we can never to public schools
so using the experience people have with
education to achieve a strategic
objective and so it works in different
ways but you can kind of see how that
fits I'm sure that I'm a little confused
because I think in general this is not
at all characteristic of this culture in
a kettle of society people indoctrinated
into believing you're not doing well at
your fault and it's a you to create your
world which i think is why we're so
comfortable with so much in your quality
and equity in this society whereas you
look at other societies say maybe
Western Europe that have social
democracy where people pay high taxes
and we have social security for health
care free education where people get
that when everybody is doing better
everybody is doing better but so I don't
really actually I'm confused about why
social security has lasted this long
because that's really not the dominant
here well it doesn't have to be the
dominant paradigm for still to be
prevalent in the experiences of a
culture and so there you can have these
different views kind of floating around
and you're absolutely right that in the
US yeah by the charts of kind of
communal to and individual we're the
most individualistic culture on the
planet so the u.s. just take that in
droves Japan in case you're curious is
actually the most communal culture in
the world and Scandinavian countries
ranked pretty highly in that as well so
the thing that's happening though is
there was a period in our history cuz we
actually have this rich history of
communities coming together like one of
the classic stories of American history
is the barn-raising story so idea that
people in the pioneering days on the
frontier had to come together and help
each other so we have the communal
component of our culture and what social
security does is it it builds off of
those values in that part of the culture
and Social Security's been harder to
make people have a distaste for that
education has so there there's an
intentional agenda to try to get rid of
social security and there and they're
trying and actually I now with the debt
crisis or some
movement they actually weaken it some
more but but it's been persistent
because the experience is intuitive and
it feeds into those values for people
within our culture a lot of people look
at is I pay in
i won by now so it still to salsa and
that's why it why it's hard to get rid
of it since people are now collecting it
they feel
dad actually it aligns with the
self-interest focus and with the
community focus and so it's got benefits
from both of them you can see how if we
think about the policy through this kind
of cognitive lens it enlightens the
space we see a lot more of what's going
on so we think how could we design
social policies so that they work the
way the social security does builds on
key elements of the culture to
perpetuate itself and generate public
good so yeah and these are just the
sorts of questions and conversations
that would help to bring all that out